# Curriculum Vitae: Chad McKell

#### ABOUT

updated: 3/24

Position Ph.D. Candidate, UC San Diego

Affiliations Center for Visual Computing, Department of Music Address 9500 Gilman Dr MC 0099, La Jolla, CA 92093

Phone +1 661 289 4215 Email cmckell@ucsd.edu Website chadmckell.com

Research My research covers mathematical modeling and numerical simulation of acoustic

systems. Current projects include geometric boundary modeling for acoustic wave simulation; non-spherical harmonics for acoustic simulation, capture, and rendering; and physical simulation of cochlear dynamics. I am especially interested in applications of

acoustic simulation in audio technology and hearing science.

### **EDUCATION**

9/19-	University of California San Diego, Ph.D. in Music (Computational Acoustics)
	Dissertation: Geometric Boundary Modeling for Acoustic Wave Simulation.
	Advisors: Albert Chern (Computer Science) and Miller Puckette (Music).
9/16-10/17	University of Edinburgh, M.S. in Acoustics and Music Technology
8/09-12/15	Wake Forest University, M.S. in Physics
6/02-8/09	Brigham Young University, B.S. in Biophysics

## **EMPLOYMENT**

3/24-	University of California San Diego, Teaching Assistant in Computer Science
6/23 - 2/24	Meta, Reality Labs Research Audio, Research Scientist Intern/Student Researcher
8/21-3/22	Meta, Reality Labs Research Audio, Research Intern/Student Researcher
9/19 - 6/23	University of California San Diego, Teaching Assistant/Researcher in Music
7/18-7/19	Applied Research in Acoustics, R&D Scientist
5/18-5/18	Moog Music, Freelance Audio Software Developer
4/17-9/17	Lofelt (acquired by Meta in 2022), Freelance Acoustics Researcher
10/14 - 8/16	J.P. Morgan/Neovest, Consulting Software Development Engineer in Test
8/12-12/12	University of North Carolina School of the Arts, Adjunct Instructor of Physics
9/09-9/11	Wake Forest University, Teaching Assistant in Physics
9/08-6/09	Brigham Young University, Tutorial Lab Assistant in Physics
8/07-3/09	Brigham Young University, Research Assistant in Philosophy

# RESEARCH ACTIVITIES

9/19- University of California San Diego, Ph.D. Student (Acoustics)

La Jolla, California. Research topics: computational acoustics, numerical simulation, differential geometry. Dissertation summary: develop mathematical and computational methods for handling open exterior boundaries in acoustic wave simulations. Committee members: Albert Chern (co-chair), Miller Puckette (co-chair), Melvin Leok, Shahrokh Yadegari, Stefan Bilbao (Univ. of Edinburgh), and Sebastian Prepeliță (Meta).

### RESEARCH ACTIVITIES CONT.

6/23-2/24	Meta, Reality Labs Research, Research Scientist Intern/Researcher (Acoustics) Redmond, Washington / La Jolla, California. Research topics: binaural audio, numerical simulation, parallel computing. Research summary: Built custom numerical simulation software using finite-difference methods in C++/CUDA for applications in virtual and augmented reality devices. Supervisor: Sebastian Prepeliță. Team Lead: Ravish Mehra.
8/21-3/22	Meta, Reality Labs Research, Research Intern/Researcher (Acoustics) La Jolla, California. Research description: see above.
7/18–7/19	<b>Applied Research in Acoustics</b> , R&D Scientist (Acoustics) Culpeper, Virginia. Research topics: underwater acoustics, matched filtering, sparse estimation, beamforming. Research summary: developed physics-based signal processing algorithms for naval sonar systems. Team Lead: Jonathan Botts.
1/17-8/17	University of Edinburgh, Master's Student (Acoustics) Edinburgh, Scotland. Research topics: speech acoustics, elastodynamics, numerical simulation. Thesis summary: developed numerical simulations of structural acoustic vibrations for commercial haptic devices. My thesis was partially funded by Lofelt, a Berlin-based haptic feedback company acquired by Meta in 2022. Advisor: Stefan Bilbao.
1/10-9/13	Wake Forest University, Master's Student (Optics) Winston-Salem, North Carolina. Research topics: optical trapping, laser characterization, fluid dynamics. Thesis summary: implemented transverse nanoparticle tracking in standing-wave Bessel beam optical traps. Advisor: Keith Bonin.

8/07–8/09 **Brigham Young University**, Undergraduate Student (Biophysics)

Provo, Utah. Research topics: *structural biology, scanning probe microscopy*. Research summary: investigated the effect of anesthetics on lipid bilayer structures using atomic force microscopy. Advisor: David Busath.

# TEACHING EXPERIENCE

# As Instructor

UNCSA		
SCI 1100	General Physics.	Fall 2012 (1 term).

# As TA

$\underline{ ext{UCSD}}$	
CSE 291	Physics Simulation. Spring 2024 (1 term) – upcoming.
MUS 5	Sound in Time. Spring 2020 (1 term).
MUS 6	Electronic Music. Fall 2020 (1 term).
MUS 15	Popular Music: David Bowie. Winter 2021 (1 term).
MUS 15	Popular Music: Video Game Music. Winter 2020 (1 term).
MUS 171	Computer Music I. Winter 2022 (1 term).
MUS 172	Computer Music II. 2021–2022 (2 terms).
WFU	
	(Community District Language 1, 100 and 1, 110 and 1, 1
PHY 113	General Physics I (Mechanics). 2009–2011 (4 terms).
PHY 114	General Physics II (E&M). Fall 2010 (1 term).

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE CONT.

## As Tutor

$\underline{\mathbf{BYU}}$	
PHSCS 105	General Physics 1 (Mechanics). 2008–2009 (2 terms).
PHSCS 106	General Physics 2 (E&M). Winter 2009 (1 term).
PHSCS 121	Principles of Physics 1 (Mechanics). 2008–2009 (2 terms).
PHSCS 123	Principles of Physics 2 (Waves/Thermo). W/Sp 2009 (2 terms).
PHSCS 220	Principles of Physics 3 (E&M). W/Sp 2009 (2 terms)

#### PH.D. COURSEWORK

CSE 167	Computer Graphics I (Jürgen Schulze)
CSE 169	Computer Animation—audit (Steve Rotenberg)
CSE 274	Discrete Differential Geometry (Albert Chern)
CSE 291	Physics Simulation—audit (Chern/Rotenberg)
CSE 299	Differential Geometry Research (Albert Chern)
MUS 206	Spatialization (Shahrokh Yadegari)
MUS 206	Deep Learning for Music Generation (Shlomo Dubnov)
MUS 206	Computational Acoustic Modeling (Tamara Smyth)
MUS 270A	Digital Audio Processing (Tamara Smyth)
MUS 270B	Analysis of Musical Sound (Miller Puckette)
MUS 270C	Compositional Algorithms (Miller Puckette)
MUS 270D	Advanced Projects in Computer Music (Puckette/Smyth)
MUS 298	Virtual Acoustics Research (Puckette/Smyth/Dubnov)
MUS 298	Differential Geometry Research (Miller Puckette)

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

### Manuscripts in Progress

(1) C. McKell, M. Nabizadeh, S. Wang, and A. Chern, "Wave simulations in infinite spacetime".

Simulating wave propagation on an infinite domain has been a long-standing computational challenge. Conventional approaches to this problem only produce wave simulations on a small subset of the infinite domain. Using the fact that wave propagation on an infinite Minkowski spacetime is equivalent to wave propagation on a bounded Minkowski spacetime under a Kelvin-like transformation, we simulate wave propagation on the entire infinite domain using a finite discretization of the bounded domain with no additional loss of accuracy from the transformation.

(2) C. McKell, Geometric Boundary Modeling for Acoustic Wave Simulation, Ph.D. Dissertation, University of California San Diego, Department of Music. Defense planned for Fall 2024. Advisors: Albert Chern (Computer Science) and Miller Puckette (Music).

In this work, I present novel geometric methods for handling open exterior boundaries in acoustic wave simulations. I first present extensions to the reflectionless discrete perfectly matched layer for the wave and Helmholtz equations. Then, I demonstrate that the conformal invariance of the wave equation under a Kelvin transform in Minkowski spacetime allows one to convert an infinite domain problem into a bounded domain problem that can be solved using standard numerical methods with no additional loss of accuracy introduced by the transform. Strategies for computing the geometric boundary models in parallel on multiple GPU nodes are presented. Applications in 3D audio as well as future work in obstacle boundary flattening are discussed.

#### PUBLICATIONS CONT.

### **Journal Articles**

(3) C. McKell and K. Bonin, "Optical corral using a standing-wave Bessel beam," *Journal of the Optical Society of America B*, Vol. 35, No. 8, 1910–1920, 2018.

## Conference Proceedings

(4) C. McKell, "Sonification of optically-ordered Brownian motion," In Proceedings of the International Computer Music Conference (ICMC), Utrecht, Netherlands, September 2016.

# Master's Theses

- (5) C. McKell, Real-Time Physical Modeling for Haptic Feedback Rendering, Master's Thesis, University of Edinburgh, Acoustics and Audio Group, 2017. Advisor: Stefan Bilbao.
- (6) C. McKell, Confinement and Tracking of Brownian Particles in a Bessel Beam Standing Wave, Master's Thesis, Wake Forest University, Department of Physics, 2015. Advisor: Keith Bonin.

# **Technical Reports**

(7) C. McKell, H. Conley, and D. Busath, "AFM study of structural changes in supported planar DPPC bilayers containing general anesthetic isoflurane," Brigham Young University, Paper 827, 2010.